He’s having the worst day of his life… Over and over again.
Groundhog Day is a romance, fantasy, comedy film directed by Harold Ramis.
A narcissistic TV weatherman, along with his attractive-but-distant producer, and his mawkish cameraman, is sent to report on
Groundhog Day in the small town of Punxsutawney, where he finds himself repeating the same day over and over.
Phil Connors, played by Bill Murray.
Rita Hanson, played by Andie MacDowell.
Larry, played by Chris Elliott.
Ned Ryerson, played by Stephen Tobolowsky.
Buster Green, played by Brian Doyle-Murray.
Nancy Taylor, played by Marita Geraghty.
Groundhog Day is a 1993 American fantasy and romantic comedy film directed
by Harold Ramis from a screenplay by him and Danny Rubin.
Starring Bill Murray, Andie MacDowell, and Chris Elliott, it tells the story of a cynical television weatherman covering the annual
Groundhog Day event in Punxsutawney, Pennsylvania, who becomes trapped in a time loop, forcing him to relive February 2 repeatedly.
The film also features Stephen Tobolowsky, Brian Doyle-Murray, Marita Geraghty, Angela
Paton, Rick Ducommun, Rick Overton, and Robin Duke in supporting roles.
Rubin conceived Groundhog Day in the early 1990s.
He wrote it as a spec script to gain meetings with producers for other work.
It eventually came to the attention of Ramis, who worked with Rubin to make his idea less
dark in tone and more palatable to a general audience by enhancing the comedy.
Murray clashed with Ramis over the script; he wanted to focus on the
philosophical elements, whereas Ramis concentrated on the comedic aspects.
Principal photography took place from March to June 1992,
almost entirely in Woodstock, Illinois.
Filming was difficult, in part because of bitterly cold weather but also
because of the ongoing conflict between Ramis and Murray.
Groundhog Day premiered at the Fox Village Theatre on February 4, 1993
and was released by Columbia Pictures on February 12.
Earning over $105 million, it became one of the year's highest-grossing films.
It also received generally positive reviews.
Critics praised the melding of sentimental and cynical moments,
and the philosophical message beneath the comedy.
It was nominated for multiple awards and won a BAFTA
Award for Best Original Screenplay.
The film marked the end of Murray and Ramis's longtime collaborative partnership,
which had produced films like Caddyshack (1980) and Ghostbusters (1984).
After filming ended, the pair did not speak to each other
until shortly before Ramis's death in 2014.
The film was a showcase for Murray; he had previously been seen primarily as a comic actor,
and his performance led to more serious roles in critically acclaimed films.
In the years since its release, the film has grown in esteem; it is often considered
among the greatest films of the 1990s and one of the greatest comedy films.
It has also had a significant effect on popular culture: the term Groundhog Day, meaning a
monotonous, unpleasant, and repetitive situation, has become part of the English lexicon.
Buddhist, Christian, and Jewish scholars have
analyzed the film as a religious allegory.
Groundhog Day is also credited with having ushered in mainstream acceptance of comedy
films with fantasy-genre elements, and popularizing time loop narratives.
In 2006, the United States Library of Congress selected the film
for preservation in the National Film Registry.
Groundhog Day was adapted into a 2016 musical, and inspired a 2019
video game sequel, Groundhog Day: Like Father Like Son.
The film explores themes of deja vu, groundhog, weather
forecast, telecaster, pennsylvania, usa.
The tone is lighthearted and emotional.